# MATEUS M. FURQUIM MENDONÇA

### Machine Learning and Software Engineer

@mfurquimdev@gmail.com

git mfurquimdev

in/mfurquimdev

@mfurquim.dev

Brazil

## **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Highly skilled software engineer with over 9 years of experience and a diverse background. Committed to team growth and innovation through effective mentoring and collaboration. Strong problem-solving skills with a passion for delivering high-quality software solutions.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### **Back-end Developer**

📋 Jan 2021 - Present

**DevGrid** 

• United Kingdom (Remote)

Managed several microservices that employ machine learning algorithms to estimate house appliances' energy consumption.

- > Achieved up to 59% improvement in **Python** write operations on **Cassandra** through the safe utilization of unlogged batches.
- > Iteratively improved domain models following **Domain Driven Design** approach, increasing efficiency in delivering new features.

#### **Embedded Software Developer**

**Autotrac** 

Nov 2019 - Aug 2020

Brasilia, DF - Brazil

Maintained security and logistic features of an embedded system for a customized hardware and Linux kernel.

- > Employed dependency injection and other SOLID principles to enhance C++ code quality and maintainability.
- > Implemented monitoring solutions to gather real-time performance data, ensuring optimal system efficiency and responsiveness.

#### **DevOps Consultant**

IBM

📋 Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Prasilia, DF - Brazil

Collaborated with multiple teams to improve observability of the back-end services of a prominent banking institution.

- > Contributed to self-discovering services feature using etcd key-value store, consistent hashing and a federation of Prometheus.
- > Employed PromQL to develop alerts that detected low performance of new deployments and potential DDoS attacks.

### **INTERN EXPERIENCE**

### **Security Software Researcher**

**LADES** at UnB

Prasilia, DF - Brazil

Enhanced an Intrusion Detection System with unsupervised machine learning to strengthen the security measures of the Brazilian Army.

- Configured a **Debian** server to capture all network packets in promiscuous mode using **Wireshark** and replay them in a controlled environment.
- > Successfully detected masked malicious network packets using K-Means clustering algorithm and distributed processing with Spark and Hadoop.

### **Software Engineer Intern**

CanAssist at UVic

📋 Jan 2015 - Apr 2015

Prasilia, DF - Brazil

Developed an elderly care embedded system which notifies relatives in case of emergency.

- > Devised an automated data-driven **regression testing** methodology, improving the efficiency of the testing cycle and ensuring alignment with requirements.
- Accomplished a low resource consumption of Raspberry Pi by rotating log using the C/C++ language and the Qt Framework.

### **EDUCATION**

# Machine Learning DevOps Engineer

**Udacity** 

Online

### **BEng. Software Engineering**

Universidade de Brasilia (UnB)

Prasilia, DF - Brazil

in Mar 2011 - Jul 2017

**University of Victoria (UVic)** 

🗣 Victoria, BC - Canada 🌞 👚 📋 Jan 2014 – Apr 2015

#### LANGUAGES

<pre></pre> <pre></pre> <pre></pre> <pre></pre> <pre></pre> <pre></pre> <pre>Working Knowledge </pre> <pre></pre> <pre>Working Knowledge</pre>	Portuguese	Mother Tongue
C/C++ Working Knowledge	English	Fluent
C/C++ Working Knowledge		
	Python	Working Knowledge
Go Intermediate Knowledge	C/C++	3
	Go	Intermediate Knowledge



</> Rust

Basic Knowledge